Guide to the Czesław Miłosz Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1934-2000; Series II; 30.44; (74 boxes)
  - Poetry
    - Individual Poems
      - "Poems published separately"
        - List, drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected, 1969 (Box 89, Folder 1206)
      - "Unpublished poems"
        Arranged roughly chronologically.
        Drafts of poems dated by Miłosz and arranged in folders labeled "Unpublished poems" and "Texts never printed."
        - "Juvenilia," holograph and typescript, 1933-1938 (Box 89, Folder 1207)
          Contains: Rachunek znowu, "Z pełną świadomoscią czego ...," "Kładliśmy jedwab ...," "Piękna jesteś ojczyzno moja, Europo...," and Jaroslawowi 20 lutego 1938 roku.
        - Wstęp, typescript, 1940 (Box 89, Folder 1208)
        - Na literata warszawskiego, typescript, 1942 (Box 89, Folder 1209)
        - Torquato Tasso (1943), typescript inscribed to Miłosz by Jarosław Iwaszkiewicz, 1970 (Box 89, Folder 1210)
        - Głosy biednych ludzi, typescript, 1943 (Box 89, Folder 1211)
        - Poems from the 1940s, holograph (Box 89, Folder 1212-1216)
        - Poems from the 1950s, holograph (Box 89, Folder 1217-1226)
        - Poems from the 1960s, holograph (Box 90, Folder 1227-1235)
        - Poems from the 1970s, holograph (Box 90, Folder 1236-1240)
        - "Jak ciężko. Żebym opowiedział komu...," typescript, 1976 (Box 90, Folder 1241)
        - "Aby uśmierzona była ciemość...," typescript, 1977 (Box 90, Folder 1242)
        - "Some text poems, never printed", 1990s (Box 90, Folder 1243)
        - "Translations with Robert Hass", 1990s (Box 90, Folder 1244-1247)
      - Other individual poems in Polish
        Arranged alphabetically by title. Untitled poems are listed according to their first line.
        - A jednak, typescript, corrected (copy), undated (Box 90, Folder 1248)
        - Adam i Ewa, typescript, undated (Box 90, Folder 1249)
        - Annalena, holograph, 1967 (Box 90, Folder 1250)
        - Antygona, holograph, circa 1956 (Box 90, Folder 1251)
        - Campo di Fiori, copy of printed version, corrected, undated (Box 90, Folder 1252)
        - Chagrin, typescript, corrected (copy), undated (Box 90, Folder 1253)
        - Człowiek-mucha, typescript and printout, undated (Box 90, Folder 1254)
        - Czytając 'Notatnik' Anny Kamieńskiej, typescript, undated (Box 90, Folder 1255)
        - Dawno i daleko (part 3), typescript, undated (Box 90, Folder 1256)
        - Do Heloizy, typescript, corrected and copies, 1984 (Box 90, Folder 1257)
        - Do pani professor w obronie honoru kota i nie tylko, printout, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1258)
        - Do poetów paryskich, typescript, undated (Box 91, Folder 1259)
        - Do Skylesa, holograph and typescript, 1943 (Box 91, Folder 1260)
        - Do zespołu "Tygodnika Powszechnego", typescript (copies), corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1261)
        - Dobro i piękno, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1262)
        - Dziękczynny, holograph, corrected, circa 1966 (Box 91, Folder 1263)
        - Felix Culpa, typescript (copy), annotated, circa 1982 (Box 91, Folder 1264)
        - Fragment czyli Kochankowie, typescript, corrected, 1950 (Box 91, Folder 1265)
        - Godzina / An Hour, offprint annotated and signed by Miłosz, 1981 (Box 91, Folder 1266)
        - Hawaje, typescript, undated (Box 91, Folder 1267)
        - "I bez myśli, bez żalu ...," holograph, circa 1948 (Box 91, Folder 1268)
        - Jeszcze jedna sprzeczność, printouts, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1269)
        - Jubilat, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1270)
        - Kassandra, holograph, undated (Box 91, Folder 1271)
        - Kto?, printout, undated (Box 91, Folder 1272)
        - Las na wyspie, typescript, undated (Box 91, Folder 1273)
        - Litwa, po piećdziesieciu dwóch latach, typescript, corrected and proof, corrected (copy), undated (Box 91, Folder 1274)
        - Łaźnia, typescript and copy, undated (Box 91, Folder 1275)
        - Mój roboczy notatnik, typescript, undated (Box 91, Folder 1276)
        - Na dobrą noc, typescript, 1944 (Box 91, Folder 1277)
        - Nie rozumiem, printout, 1990s (Box 91, Folder 1278)
        - Nieobjęta ziemia, fragments, holograph, corrected, circa 1983 (Box 91, Folder 1279)
        - Notatnik: Brzegi Lemanu, typescript, 1953 (Box 91, Folder 1280)
        - Notatnik: Dordogne, typescript, corrected, 1952 (Box 91, Folder 1281)
        - Notatnik: Europa, typescript, corrected, 1952 (Box 91, Folder 1282)
        - Nowy kraj, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1283)
        - O duszy nieśmiertelnej, printout, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1284)
        - Odczyt, typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1285)
        - "Okazuje się, że to było ....," typescript, undated (Box 91, Folder 1286)
        - Pieniądz, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1287)
        - Po osiemdziesiątce, holograph and printout, undated (Box 91, Folder 1288)
        - Pobłażanie, typescript, undated (Box 91, Folder 1289)
        - Potomny, typescript, corrected and copies, 1985 (Box 91, Folder 1290)
        - Powrót, typescript, undated (Box 91, Folder 1291)
        - Prośba, typescript and copy (Box 91, Folder 1292)
        - Przeszłość, typescript, corrected and copy, undated (Box 91, Folder 1293)
        - Przybytek, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1294)
        - Rozmowa z Jeanne, typescript, corrected, 1984 (Box 91, Folder 1295)
        - Rozmowa z Jeanne I, typescript, corrected, 1984 (Box 91, Folder 1296)
        - Rycerz, printout, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1297)
        - Ściana muzeum, printout, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1298)
        - Sens, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1299)
        - Słowo i miecz, holograph and typescript carbon, 1942 (Box 91, Folder 1300)
        - Sobie samemu do sztambucha na nowy rok 1950, drafts, holograph, corrected (Box 91, Folder 1301)
        - Sobowtór, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1302)
        - Stan poetycki, holograph, 1977 (Box 91, Folder 1303)
        - Stwarzanie świata, typescript, undated (Box 91, Folder 1304)
        - Ta planeta, printout, undated (Box 91, Folder 1305)
        - Traktat moralny, typescript, 1951-1952 (Box 91, Folder 1306)
          Number 4 of 5 exemplars, printed at U-W K.C.N.
        - Trwałość, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1307)
        - Uczestnik, typescript and copies, undated (Box 91, Folder 1308)
        - Wanda, printout, after 1985 (Box 91, Folder 1309)
        - Wcielony, typescript, corrected (copy), undated (Box 91, Folder 1310)
        - Wezwanie, typescript. corrected, 1953 (Box 91, Folder 1311)
        - Wiersz na koniec stulecia, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1312)
        - Wiersze I-V, typescript carbon, 1937 (Box 91, Folder 1313)
        - "Wiersze ulotne" ( Perla and Gwiazda ), typescript, 1944 (Box 91, Folder 1314)
        - Zbieranie moreli, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 91, Folder 1315)
        - Ze sztambucha Wandy Telakowskiej (occasional to Wanda Telakowska), copies of 1948 holograph and circa 1988 typescript, undated (Box 91, Folder 1316)
        - Zen codzienny, holograph, corrected, circa 1988 (Box 91, Folder 1317)
        - Various poems, photocopies, undated (Box 91, Folder 1318)
        - Unidentified fragments, holograph and typescript, 1950s-1990s (Box 91, Folder 1319-1324)
      - Other Individual Poems, Autotranslations
        Consists of drafts, many corrected, that reveal the translation process. Most autotranslations were written by Miłosz in collaboration with others, including Robert Hass, Renata Gorczyński, and Leonard Nathan.
        - L'Accélération de l'histoire, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 92, Folder 1325)
        - At Yale, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1326)
        - Before a landscape, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1327)
        - Beinecke Library, typescript and copy, undated (Box 92, Folder 1328)
        - Bells in winter, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1329)
        - Berkeley, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1330)
        - Body, printouts, undated (Box 92, Folder 1331)
        - Bypassing Rue Descartes, printed version (copy), corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1332)
        - Cafe Greco, printout, undated (Box 92, Folder 1333)
        - Capri, printouts, undated (Box 92, Folder 1334)
        - Child of Europe, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1335)
        - A Christian looks at the ghetto, holograph, undated (Box 92, Folder 1336)
        - City of my youth, printout, undated (Box 92, Folder 1337)
        - City without a name, holograph, undated (Box 92, Folder 1338)
        - Concert, holograph, undated (Box 92, Folder 1339)
        - A confession, typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1340)
        - Confessions of an ornithologist (prose poem), typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1341)
        - Conversation with Jeanne, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1342)
        - Creating the world, typescripts, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1343)
        - Dante, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1344)
        - December 1, typescript, uncorrected and corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1345)
        - Destiny, typescript, undated (Box 92, Folder 1346)
        - Durability, typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1347)
        - Enfant d'Europe, holograph, undated (Box 92, Folder 1348)
          Unidentified translator; written in Miłosz's hand.
        - The eyes, holograph, undated (Box 92, Folder 1349)
        - Far west, holograph and printout, undated (Box 92, Folder 1350)
        - Fulfillment, typescript and copy, undated (Box 92, Folder 1351)
        - Good night, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1352)
        - How it should be in heaven, typescript carbon and printouts, undated (Box 92, Folder 1353)
        - In music, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1354)
        - In Warsaw, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1355)
        - Inheritor, typescript, undated (Box 92, Folder 1356)
        - "It is December 31/ 11 o'clock in the morning ...," holograph, undated (Box 92, Folder 1357)
        - It was winter, typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1358)
        - Lauda (excerpts), holograph and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1359)
        - A lecture, printouts, undated (Box 92, Folder 1360)
        - A man-fly, printout, corrected and proof, corrected, 1992 (Box 92, Folder 1361)
        - Mary Magdalen and I, typescript, undated (Box 92, Folder 1362)
        - Meaning, holograph, undated (Box 92, Folder 1363)
        - Meditation, typescript (copy) and proof, corrected, 1991 (Box 92, Folder 1364)
        - My Lithuanian childhood: A smithy, typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1365)
        - A nation, holograph and typescript (Box 92, Folder 1366)
          Includes a letter from Robert Hass to Miłosz and portions handwritten [by Robert Hass?].
        - A new country, typescript and printout, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1367)
        - An old woman poet, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1368)
        - One, typescript, undated (Box 92, Folder 1369)
        - Outlines of thought, printout, undated (Box 92, Folder 1370)
        - Page 25 from The separate notebooks, typescript, corrected and unknown hand (copy), undated (Box 92, Folder 1371)
        - Pages concerning the years of independence, holograph, undated (Box 92, Folder 1372)
        - The path, typescript, undated (Box 92, Folder 1373)
        - Philology, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1374)
        - A photograph, printout, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1375)
        - Poem for the end of the century, typescript, corrected and proof, corrected, 1991 (Box 92, Folder 1376)
        - Poet at seventy, holograph, undated (Box 92, Folder 1377)
        - Powers, printout, undated (Box 92, Folder 1378)
        - A prayer, typescript, undated (Box 92, Folder 1379)
        - A question from the hall, printouts, some corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1380)
        - Reading 'Notebook' by Anna Kamieńska, typescript (copy), undated (Box 92, Folder 1381)
        - Reconciliation, typescripts, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1382)
        - Regions, typescript and copy, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1383)
        - Return, printout (copy), corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1384)
        - Rivers, typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1385)
        - Sarajevo, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1386)
        - Six lectures in verse, holograph and typescript (copy), undated (Box 92, Folder 1387)
        - So little, typescript, undated (Box 92, Folder 1388)
        - Song on porcelain, holograph and printout, undated (Box 92, Folder 1389)
        - Songs of Adrian Zieliński, holograph, undated (Box 92, Folder 1390)
        - Spider, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1391)
        - Stay away from me, printout, undated (Box 92, Folder 1392)
        - A story, holograph, undated (Box 92, Folder 1393)
        - This world, printouts, undated (Box 92, Folder 1394)
        - The thistle, the nettle, typescript, corrected and proof, 1989 (Box 92, Folder 1395)
        - The titanic, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 92, Folder 1396)
        - To Allen Ginsberg, printout, undated (Box 92, Folder 1397)
        - To my Daimonion, printouts, undated (Box 92, Folder 1398)
        - Today I walked through a garden, typescript, undated (Box 93, Folder 1399)
        - Treatise on poetry, printout, corrected and proof, corrected (copy), undated (Box 93, Folder 1400)
        - Veni creator, holograph, undated (Box 93, Folder 1401)
          Includes: When the moon, holograph
        - When the moon
          See: Veni creator
        - Why?, printouts and printed version, 1992, undated (Box 93, Folder 1402)
        - The year 1911, holograph, undated (Box 93, Folder 1403)
        - You who wronged, holograph, undated (Box 93, Folder 1404)
        - [Poems for Dreamland ?] (a documentary film by Richard Lourie), typescript, corrected, circa 1983 (Box 93, Folder 1405)
        - Various titles, copies, 1985, undated (Box 93, Folder 1406)
        - Submissions to poetry journals and correspondence with publishers, 1991-1997, undated (Box 93, Folder 1407-1409)
        - Unidentified fragments, holograph, typescript and printout, undated (Box 93, Folder 1410-1411)
  - Prose
    The Prose subseries is organized under two headings: Major Works of Prose and Essays and Other Shorter Works of Prose.
    In addition to works in their original language, the subseries includes translations (on which Miłosz often collaborated) into English, Polish and French.
    - Major Works in Prose
      - Beginning with my streets
        English translation by Madeline G. Levine of Zaczynając od moich ulic.
        - Preface by Miłosz, drafts, holograph and printout, [1990] (Box 94, Folder 1412-1413)
        - Drafts, printout, [1990] (Box 94, Folder 1414-1415)
          Includes essays that were later omitted from the printed volume.
        - Correspondence and notes, 1989-1990 (Box 94, Folder 1416)
      - The captive mind
        English translation of Zniewolony umysł by Jane Zielonko.
        - "Instead of a preface" (introduction by Miłosz), typescript carbon, undated (Box 94, Folder 1417)
        - Response to a questionnaire from A. A. Knopf, holograph, circa 1953 (Box 94, Folder 1418)
          Includes notes by Jeanne Hersch.
      - Człowiek wśród skorpionów: Studium o Stanisławie Brzozowskim, Drafts, holograph and typescript, [1962] (Box 94, Folder 1419-1423)
      - Dolina Issy
        - Draft, holograph, undated (Box 94, Folder 1424)
        - Proof (Wydawnictwo Literackie, Kraków), 1981 (Box 95, Folder 1425-1428)
        - {Empty folder} (Box 95, Folder 1429)
      - Emperor of the earth: Modes of eccentric vision
        - Draft, typescript, [1974] (Box 95, Folder 1430-1435)
        - Draft, typescript (copy), undated (Box 96, Folder 1436-1440)
      - Góry Parnasu
        - Draft, holograph, undated (Box 96, Folder 1441)
        - Draft (shortened version), typescript, undated (Box 96, Folder 1442)
      - Historia literatury polskiej, Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 96, Folder 1443-1445)
        Polish translation of History of Polish literature by Elżbieta Morawiec.
      - History of Polish literature
        - First draft, typescript, corrected, [1969] (Box 97, Folder 1446-1453)
          Original manuscript was damaged by mold and is stored in Restricted Fragile Papers. Preservation photocopies are provided for reference use.
        - "Texts relevant to History of Polish literature," handwritten notes and copies, [1969] (Box 97, Folder 1454)
          Original manuscript was damaged by mold. Preservation photocopies are provided for reference use.
        - Second draft, typescript, corrected, [1969] (Box 97, Folder 1455-1456)
        - Second draft (continued), typescript, corrected, [1969] (Box 98, Folder 1457-1462)
        - Third draft, typescript, corrected, [1969] (Box 99, Folder 1463-1466)
        - Proof, table of contents and title page, 1969 (Box 99, Folder 1467)
        - Notes and revisions for the 1983 edition, 1982 (Box 99, Folder 1468)
      - Kontynenty
        - Introduction to the section "Francja," draft, typescript, corrected, 1958 (Box 99, Folder 1469)
        - Setting copy for 1999 edition, copies of printed versions, corrected, 1990s (Box 99, Folder 1470-1471)
      - Land of Ulro
        English translation of Ziemia Ulro by Louis Iribarne.
        - Selections, draft, copy of typescript, undated (Box 99, Folder 1472)
        - Proofs, 1984
      - Legendy nowoczesności: Eseje okupacyjne, Material that was printed in the 1996 publication, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1940s (Box 100, Folder 1473-1475)
      - Ogród nauk
        - Drafts, holograph, corrected, 1970s (Box 100, Folder 1476-1479)
        - Introduction, drafts, typescript, corrected, 1970s (Box 100, Folder 1480)
      - Prywatne obowiązki
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, 1960s (Box 100, Folder 1481-1482)
          Microfilm available
        - Draft (continued), holograph, corrected, 1960s (Box 101, Folder 1483)
        - Draft (portions), typescript, corrected, 1963 (Box 101, Folder 1484)
        - Introduction, drafts, typescript, corrected, 1972 (Box 101, Folder 1485)
      - Rodzinna Europa
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, 1950s (Box 101, Folder 1486)
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, 1950s (Box 101, Folder 1487-1489)
        - Variant drafts, holograph, corrected, 1950s (Box 101, Folder 1490)
      - Rok myśliwego
        - Audio cassettes, 1987-1988 (Box 102, Folder 1491-1501)
          Restricted pending digital reformatting.
        - Notebooks (copy), 1988 (Box 103, Folder 1502-1509)
        - Draft (fragment), holograph, corrected, 1988 (Box 103, Folder 1510)
        - Draft, printout and copies, corrected, 1988 (Box 104, Folder 1511-1518)
        - Draft (fragment), typescript, corrected (copy), undated (Box 104, Folder 1519)
      - Striving towards being, proofs, corrected, 1996-1997 (Box 105, Folder 1520-1523)
      - Szukanie ojczyzny, Setting copy, typescript and copies, [1992] (Box 105, Folder 1524-1527)
      - Świadectwo poezji
        - Draft, copy of typescript, [1983] (Box 106, Folder 1528)
        - Errata, copy of typescript, [1983] (Box 106, Folder 1529)
      - The Valley of Issa, synopsis in English, typescript, undated (Box 106, Folder 1530)
      - Vilnius - Wilno - Vilnia, setting copy, printouts and copies of printed versions, [1995] (Box 106, Folder 1531)
        A planned collection of Polish-language writings on Vilnius.
      - Visions from San Francisco Bay, introduction, draft, holograph, [1982] (Box 106, Folder 1532)
      - Widzenia nad Zatoką San Francisco
        - Draft, holograph, [1969] (Box 106, Folder 1533-1534)
        - Variant drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1960s (Box 106, Folder 1535-1536)
        - Introduction, drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, 1960s (Box 106, Folder 1537-1538)
      - The witness of poetry, draft, typescript, corrected, circa 1983 (Box 107, Folder 1539-1540)
      - A year of the hunter
        English translation of Rok myśliwego by Madeline Levine.
        - Setting copy, corrected, 1994 (Box 107, Folder 1541-1543)
        - Proofs, corrected, 1994 (Box 108, Folder 1544-1547)
      - Zaczynając od moich ulic, setting copy, [1985] (Box 109, Folder 1548-1556)
      - Zaraz po wojnie: Korespondencja z pisarzami, draft, printouts and copies of typescript, 1948, 1998 (Box 110, Folder 1557-1561)
      - Zdobycie władzy, draft, holograph, circa 1955 (Box 110, Folder 1562)
      - Ziemia Ulro
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, [1970s] (Box 110, Folder 1563-1566)
        - Draft (continued), holograph, corrected, [1970s] (Box 111, Folder 1567-1574)
        - Draft (fragments), typescript and copy of typescript, undated (Box 112, Folder 1575-1576)
      - Zniewolony umysł
        - First draft, holograph, 1950s (Box 112, Folder 1577-1579)
        - Fragments and notes, 1950s (Box 112, Folder 1580-1581)
        - Printed version, microfiche reproduction, undated (Box 112, Folder 1582)
      - Życie na wyspach, post-scriptum, drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1990 (Box 112, Folder 1583)
      - Various titles, book jackets and artwork, 1953-1986, undated (Box 112, Folder 1584-1586)
      - Unidentified prose works, fragments and tables of contents, undated (Box 112, Folder 1587)
    - Essays and Other Shorter Works of Prose
      Material is organized under four sub-headings by language: Polish, English, French, and German. Writings are arranged alphabetically by title under each heading. Untitled writings are arranged roughly chronologically and filed at the end of each alphabetical listing.
      Other letters to editors are filed in General Correspondence, as noted in folder titles of that subseries. Essays that were originally published separately and later collected into volumes (such as those printed in Kontynenty ) are filed under this heading.
      - Polish
        - "3 opowiastki moralne," draft, holograph, corrected, 1940s (Box 113, Folder 1588)
        - 82 wiersze i poematy, by Joseph Brodsky (foreword by Miłosz), holograph and copy of typescript, corrected, 1988 (Box 113, Folder 1589)
        - "Adam Mickiewicz," draft, holograph, 1955 (Box 113, Folder 1590)
        - "Ameryka Łacińska," draft, holograph, corrected, 1940s (Box 113, Folder 1591)
        - "Amerykańscy pisarze w obronie Pabla Nerudy," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1947 or 1948 (Box 113, Folder 1592)
        - "Andrzej Trzebiński," draft, typescript carbon, 1960 (Box 113, Folder 1593)
        - "Anti-semitism in Poland" (Polish language version), drafts, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, 1957 (Box 113, Folder 1594)
        - "Apollo Nałęcz Korzeniowski," copy of 1956 printed version, undated (Box 113, Folder 1595)
        - "Azjatycka podróż Mertona," draft, typescript, 1997? (Box 113, Folder 1596)
        - "Bieliński i jednorożec," drafts, typescript, corrected, undated (1990s or 2000s) (Box 113, Folder 1597)
          One version is translated from the French ("Bieliński et la licorne") by Monika Makowska, with corrections by Miłosz.
        - "Braterski rozmówca," drafts, typescript and printed version, 1995 (Box 113, Folder 1598)
          Translated from the French ("L'interlocuteur fraternal") by Miłosz.